<metadata>
 <datum name=__removed valuen=1>
 <datum name=author value="0">
 <datum name=description value="">
 <datum name=external_use value="">
 <datum name=http-content-type value="text/xml">
 <datum name=keywords value="">
 <datum name=stationery value="">
 <datum name=stationery_md_flags value="">
 <datum name=template value="tutorial.xsl">
 <datum name=title value="Some Examples of Modules">
</metadata>
<manual>

A module is a sort of "plug-in": a software package that can easily
be used by other programmers. Modules can contain methods, classes,
constants, and also other modules. We will use the term **members**
for something, such as a method, that a module contains. Some modules
are written in Pike, but C and C++ can also be used.

Pike is delivered with a number of useful modules.
Here is a list of a few of the more interesting modules.

<list type="ul">
<item name="Stdio">
This module is used for reading and writing files, and also for
communication over the Internet, and for text-based dialogues with the
user. We have used the **Stdio** module in several examples in this
tutorial.
</item>

<item name="GTK">
A toolkit for creating graphical user interfaces, with windows,
buttons and so on.
</item>

<item name="Image">
Processing and manipulation of pictures.
</item>

<item name="Protocols">
Various protocols, i e ways of communicating. One of these is
`Protocols.HTTP`, which is used to communicate with World Wide
Web servers in order to retrieve web pages. Some other supported
protocols are **DNS**, **IMAP**, **IRC**, **LDAP**,
**LysKOM**, **NNTP**, **SMTP**, and **TELNET**.
</item>

<item name="MIME">
Support for coding and encoding using MIME, which is used in
electronic mail.
</item>

<item name="Crypto">
Support for cryptography.
</item>

<item name="Calendar">
Support for various calendar and date formats.
</item>

<item name="Mysql">
This module lets Pike use SQL database queries, with the mySQL
database server.
</item>

<item name="Thread">
Support for threaded execution of Pike programs.
</item>

<item name="Process">
Functions to start and control other processes.
</item>

<item name="Getopt">
Routines to interpret and handle command line options.
</item>

<item name="LR">
LALR(1) parser generator.
</item>

<item name="Yp">
Network Information System support.
</item>

<item name="Gz">
Support for unpacking compressed files.
</item>

<item name="Regexp">
Support for matching so-called regular expressions.
</item>
</list>

Depending on which operating system you are using, and on exactly
how Pike was installed on your system, some of these modules may not
be available.

</manual>
